Guide to the Spruille Braden Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Spruille Braden Papers
1903-1977.
Braden, Spruille, 1894-1978
34 linear ft (ca. 36,160 items in 70 boxes, 150 volumes, 1 folder, & 1 scrapbook.
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0143
4079451
This collection contains correspondence, speeches, manuscripts, documents, photographs, printed material and audiovisual material of Spruille Braden, 1894-1978, American diplomat and mining engineer.
Biographical Note
American diplomat, mining engineer. Braden (1894-1978) was a diplomat in numerous Latin American countries and was particularly well known for his role as the American Representative to the Chaco Peace Conference, 1935-1939, and for his opposition to the Peron regime in Argentina in the 1940s.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, speeches, manuscripts, documents, photographs, printed material, and audio visual material, primarily relating to Braden's career as a diplomat. Also included are files from his tenure as Assistant Secretary of State for Latin American Affairs, 1945-1947. The numerous scrapbooks in the collection contain clippings, photographs, and invitations. Major correspondents include Adolf A. Berle, Jr., Homer S. Cummings, James A. Farley, Barry Goldwater, Ernest Hemingway, John Edgar Hoover, Cordell Hull, Frances Kellor, Edward I. Koch, Archibald MacLeish, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Leo S. Rowe, Edward R. Stettinius, Jr., Thomas J. Watson, and Sumner Welles.
Arrangement
Selected materials cataloged; remainder arranged. This collection is arranged in three series:
Series I: Correspondence and Catalogued Items
Series II: Appearances
Series III: Manuscripts, Documents and Miscellaneous
Subjects
United States.--Assistant Secretary of State for Latin American Affairs.; Chaco Peace Conference (1935-1939 :--Buenos Aires, Argentina); Berle, Adolf Augustus, 1895-1971.; Cummings, Homer S. (Homer Stillé), 1870-1956.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-1998.; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961.; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955.; Kellor, Frances, 1873-1952.; Koch, Ed, 1924-; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; Perón, Juan Domingo, 1895-1974.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1908-1979.; Rowe, L. S. (Leo Stanton), 1871-1946.; Stettinius, Edward R. (Edward Reilly), 1900-1949.; Latin America--Foreign relations.; Argentina--Politics and government--1943-; United States--Foreign relations--Latin America.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; Audiovisual materials.; Photoprints.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches.; Diplomats.; Mining engineers.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: Boxes 4-72. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1958 M-58 Braden, Spruille Gift
Gift of Spruille Braden, 1958; gift of the Braden family, 1978; gift of William Braden, 1981.
- Series I: Correspondence and Catalogued Items
  This series contains catalouged correspondence, manuscripts and photographs. This series also contains general and diplomatic corrospondence arranged chronologically and alphabetically.
  - Catalogued Correspondence
    - Acheson, Dean (Box 1)
    - Aldrich, Winthrop W. (Box 1)
    - Ayala, Eusebio (Box 1)
    - Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio (Box 1)
    - Berle, Adolf A., Jr. (Box 1)
    - Biddle, Francis (Box 1)
    - Bowers, Claude G. (Box 1)
    - Bowman, Isaiah (Box 1)
    - Buckley, James L. (Box 1)
    - Buckley, William F., Jr. (Box 1)
    - Byrnes, James F. (Box 1)
    - Christy, Howard Chandler (Box 1)
    - Church, Frank (Box 1)
    - Clayton, William L. (Box 1)
    - Clemens, Cyril (Box 1)
    - Cooke, Terence. Cardinal (Box 1)
    - Crawford, Joan (Box 1)
    - Cummings. Homer S. (Box 1)
    - Davidson, Jo (Box 1)
    - Davila, Carlos. (Box 1)
    - Davis, John W. (Box 1)
    - Duggan, Stephen F. (Box 1)
    - Dulles, John Foster (Box 1)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight David (Box 1)
    - Farley, James A. (Box 1)
    - Gellhorn, Martha (Box 1)
    - Goldwater, Barry (Box 1)
    - Grew, Joseph C. (Box 1)
    - Gruening, Ernest (Box 1)
    - Gunther. John (Box 1)
    - Hayes, Carlton J.H. (Box 1)
    - Hemingway, Ernest (Box 1)
    - Hoover, John Edgar (Box 1)
    - Hull, Cordell (Box 1)
    - Javitz, Jacob K. (Box 2)
    - Johnson, Lyndon B. (Box 2)
    - Kellor, Frances (Box 2)
    - King, Willard V. (Box 2)
    - Knox, Frank (Box 2)
    - Koch, Edward I. (Box 2)
    - Lane, Arthur Bliss (Box 2)
    - Lewisohn, Sam A. (Box 2)
    - Lippmano, Walter (Box 2)
    - Lodge, John Davis (Box 2)
    - Long, Breckinridge (Box 2)
    - MacLeish, Archibald. (Box 2)
    - McNutt, Paul V. (Box 2)
    - Meany, George (Box 2)
    - Merrill, John L. (Box 2)
    - Moynihan, Daniel Patrick (Box 2)
    - Ospina Perez, Mariano (Box 2)
    - Pearson, Drew (Box 2)
    - Reagan, Ronald (Box 2)
    - Reid, Whitelaw (Box 2)
    - Rickenbacker, Edward (Box 2)
    - Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Box 2)
    - Rodino, Peter W., Jr. (Box 2)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor Roosevelt (Mrs. Franklin D.) (Box 2)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano (Box 2)
    - Roosevelt, Nicholas (Box 2)
    - Rowe, Leo S. (Box 2)
    - Skouras, Spyros P. (Box 3)
    - Spellman, Francis Joseph, Cardinal (Box 3)
    - Stettinius, Edward R., -Tr. (Box 3)
    - Sulzberger, Arthur Mays (Box 3)
    - Sulzberger, Iphigene Ochs (Box 3)
    - Swope, Herbert Bayard (Box 3)
    - Tejada Gorzano, Jose Luis 1881-1938 (Box 3)
    - Trujillo Molina, Rafael Leonidas, 1891- (Box 3)
    - Truman, Harry S. (Box 3)
    - Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Box 3)
    - Wallace, Henry A. (Box 3)
    - Watson, Thomas J. (Box 3)
    - Welch, Robert (Box 3)
    - Welles, Sumner (Box 3)
    - Wilder, Thornton (Box 3)
  - Catalogued Manuscripts
    - Gunther, John.
      - The Chaco War (Box 3)
      - Hail Colombia (Box 3)
  - Catalogued photographs:
    - Cummings, Homer (Box 3)
    - Grew, Joseph C. (Box 3)
    - Olav V, King of Norway (Box 3)
    - Rowe, Leo S. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Diplomatic
    - 1935 (Box 4)
    - 1936-1938 - U.S. Dept. of State Despatches (Box 4)
    - 1936
      - A-D (Box 4)
      - E-G (Box 5)
      - H-N (Box 5)
      - O-Z (Box 5)
    - 1937
      - A-K (Box 6)
      - L-Z (Box 6)
    - 1938
      - A-H (Box 6)
      - J-Z (Box 6)
    - 1939 (Box 7)
    - 1940 (Box 7)
    - 1941
      - A-M (Box 7)
      - N-Z (Box 7)
    - 1942
      - A-Braden (Box 8)
      - Braden-Bz (Box 8)
      - C (Box 8)
      - D-H (Box 8)
      - I-L (Box 9)
      - M-R (Box 9)
      - S-We (Box 9)
      - Wr-Z (Box 9)
    - 1943
      - A-Be (Box 10)
      - Briggs (Box 10)
      - B misc. - C (Box 10)
      - D-E (Box 10)
      - F-I (Box 11)
      - J-L (Box 11)
      - M-N (Box 11)
      - O-R (Box 11)
      - S-T (Box 12)
      - U-Z (Box 12)
    - 1944
      - A-Bo (Box 12)
      - Br-Bz (Box 12)
      - B misc. (Box 13)
      - C misc. (Box 13)
      - C-E (Box 13)
      - F-J (Box 13)
      - K-M (Box 14)
      - M (Box 14)
      - N-P (Box 14)
      - R (Box 14)
      - S (Box 15)
      - T-Z (Box 15)
    - 1945
      - Cuba
        - A (Box 15)
        - B (Box 15)
        - C-F (Box 16)
        - G-K (Box 16)
        - L-Na (Box 16)
        - Ne-P (Box 16)
        - R-S (Box 17)
        - S-Z (Box 17)
      - Argentine Transfer (Argentina) (Box 18)
        - A-B (Box 18)
        - C-F (Box 18)
        - G-L (Box 18)
        - M-P (Box 18)
        - Q-S (Box 19)
        - T-Z (Box 19)
      - Washington Transfer -, (2 Folders) (Box 19)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 20)
      - A-D (Box 20)
      - E-I (Box 20)
      - Q-V (Box 20)
      - W-Z (Box 20)
    - Condolences, 1943 (Box 21)
    - Congratualtions, 1945
      - A-L (Box 21)
      - M-Z (Box 21)
    - Invitations
      - 1938 (Box 21)
      - 1945 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, General (Box 22)
    - Argentina, 1945-1947 (Box 22)
    - Braden, Spruille
      - Resignation, 1947 (Box 22)
      - Statements and Articles, 1945-1947 (Box 22)
    - Cabot, John M., 1945-1947 (Box 22)
    - Fan Mail, 1945-1947 (Box 22)
    - Messersmith, G.S., 1945-1946 (Box 22)
    - New York City Anti-Crime Committee, 1955-1957 (Box 22)
    - Thompson, Scott, 1945-1947 (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 22)
    - Braden, Spruille (Box 23)
      - Childhood letters, 1903-1904 (Box 23)
      - Family letters, Ca. 1925-1953 (Box 23)
      - (1929-1933) - Letters to and from his father (Box 23)
    - Braden, William - Personal Files
      - January-December 1934 (Box 23)
      - January-June 1935 (Box 23)
    - Briggs, Ellis 0. - 2 Folders (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 24)
      - 1909-1959 and not dated (Box 24)
      - 1960-1977 (Box 24)
      - U.S. Dept. of State Memoranda (Box 24)
- Series II: Appearances
  This series contains documents relating to speeches and conference attendence by Braden. This series is arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
  - Speeches
    - Albright College, 2 June 1946 (Box 25)
    - American Geographical Society, 19 December 1945 (Box 25)
    - American Institute of Mining Engineers, New York, 19 March 1947, (2 Folders) (Box 25)
    - American Club, 26 May 1942 (Box 25)
    - Argentina (Box 25)
    - Boston Conference on Distribution, 14 October 1946 (Box 25)
    - Boston Trip, October I946 - Off the record (Box 25)
    - Bromley Lectureship at Yale University, 18 December 1945, (2 Folders) (Box 25)
    - Celestials, 13 February 1946 (Box 25)
    - Clark University, 26 May 1946 (Box 25)
    - Cleveland Commission on Foreign Relations; Chicago - Off the record (Box 25)
    - Columbia University Club, 2 March 1946 (Box 25)
    - Departmental Group - Mr. Braden and Mr. Spaeth, 24 September 1946 (Box 25)
    - Executives' Club of Chicago, 13 September 1946, (3 Folders) (Box 25)
    - Foreign Policy Association, and Pan American Association at Philadelphia, 13 April 1946 (Box 26)
    - Hemispheric Insurance, 15 May 1946 (Box 26)
    - Historians Luncheon, 14 December 1945 (Box 26)
    - House Foreign Affairs Committee, 26 July 1946 (Box 26)
    - Johns Hopkins University 1939 (Box 26)
    - Litoral University, Buenos Aires, 21 July, 1945 (Box 26)
    - Mass Media Representatives - Off the record (Box 26)
    - Meet the Press (American Mercury) (Box 26)
    - Montana School of Mines, 7 June 1947 (Box 26)
    - NBC Broadcast
      - 21 December 1946 (Box 26)
      - 5 January 1946, (2 Folders) (Box 26)
    - National Democratic Club, 23 March 1946 (Box 26)
    - National Trade Council, 14 November 1945 (Box 26)
    - Navy Day, 27 October 1945 (Box 26)
    - New York Herald Tribune High School Forum, 8 March 1947 (Box 26)
    - New York Times - To General Federation of Women's Clubs, 27 March 1946 (Box 26)
    - Pan American Union - Dr. Leo S. Rowe's Memorial (Box 27)
    - Pan American Day - Radio Greetings to Latin America, 1947 (Box 27)
    - Pan American Union - Tribute to Franklin D. Roosevelt, November, 1946 (Box 27)
    - Peron University, La Plata, 10 June 1944 (Box 27)
    - Roosevelt Memorial Exhibit, Pan American Union (Box 27)
    - Rutgers University, 26 October 1945 (Box 27)
    - Santander and Jefferson (Box 27)
    - University Club, 19 January 1946 (Box 27)
    - Wendell L. Willkie Awards for Negro Journalism, 1 March 1946 (Box 27)
    - Chronological
      - 1933-1938 (Box 27)
      - 1938-1942 (Box 27)
      - 1942-1943, (2 Folders) (Box 28)
      - 1943, (2 Folders) (Box 28)
      - 1944 (Box 29)
      - 1945 (Box 29)
      - 1946-1947 (Box 29)
      - 1945-1950 (Box 30)
      - 1946-1947 (Box 30)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1950s (Box 30)
      - Pre-State Department (Box 30)
      - Material for Speeches (Box 30)
      - General (Box 30)
  - Conferences (Box 31)
    - Pan American Commercial Conference, Buenos Aires, 1935, (2 Folders)
      - Instructions to delegates (Box 31)
    - 7th International Conference of American States, 1932-1933 (Box 32)
      - Instructions to delegates (Box 32)
    - Inter-American Conference for the Maintenance of Peace, 1936 (Box 32)
  - Appointment Books and Wedding Guest Lists, 1937, 1942-1945 (Box 33)
- Series III: Manuscripts, Documents and Miscellaneous
  This series contains financial and legal documents, manuscripts, scrapbooks, pamphlets, phonograph records, movie film and books from the library of Spruille Braden. Braden library items in this series include approximately 150 volumes inscribed to or by Braden; annotated by, citing, or by Braden; and miscellaneous works. Most concern South America, diplomacy, or ultraconservative politics.
  - Financial and Legal Documents, 1924-1943 (Box 34)
    - Accounting Memos (Box 34)
    - Accounts (Box 34)
    - Barranquilla Electric Project, 1926 (Box 34)
    - Contracts (Box 34)
    - Insurance (Box 34)
    - Mexican Gas Negotiations (Box 34)
    - Munoz, Sara (Box 34)
    - Receipts, (2 Folders) (Box 34)
    - Romero (Box 34)
  - Subject File
    - Ambassadorship, 1933 (Box 35)
    - American Arbitration Association (Box 35)
    - Argentina
      - General, (2 Folders) (Box 35)
        - 1944-1945 (Box 35)
        - 1945 (Box 35)
      - AFL Report, 10 March 1947 (Box 35)
      - Magazine Articles (Box 35)
      - Memorandum to President Truman, July 1946 (Box 35)
      - Peron, Juan - "Blue and White Book" (Box 35)
      - Press, 1945 (Box 36)
      - Wells, Robert C, Reports, 1945-1946, (3 Folders) (Box 36)
    - Argentina's Compliance with.. .Agreements - Memorandum, 1946 (Box 36)
    - Braden Family Genealogy (Box 36)
    - Chaco, 1942-1943 (Box 36)
    - Cienfuegos - 1942 Trip - Correspondence and related items (Box 36)
    - Clark University Honorary Degree, 1946 (Box 36)
    - Dictatorships and Disreputable Governments (Box 36)
    - Inter-American Commerical Arbitration Commission (Box 36)
    - Military and Naval Information (Box 37)
    - Montana - 1947 Trip (Box 37)
    - New York City Anti-Crime Committee (Box 37)
    - Paraguay (Box 37)
    - Passports, Cancelled Diplomatic - Braden Family (Box 37)
    - Personnel Investigations, Inter-Office Committee on (Box 37)
    - Reference File (Box 37)
    - Schuyler, Chadwich and Burnham (Box 37)
    - Stonehurst Apartments (Box 37)
    - Tetens, T.H. (Box 37)
    - Tomlinson, Edward (Box 37)
    - UNESCO (Box 37)
  - Manuscripts and Documents, Miscellaneous
    - Undated (Box 38)
    - 1930s (Box 38)
    - 1945-1947 (Box 38)
    - 1948-1952 (Box 38)
    - Government Reports, 1946 (Box 38)
    - General (Box 39)
    - Braden, Spruille. [Diplomats and Demagogues.] 1966 draft ms. (Box 39)
    - Certificates, Diplomas (Box 39)
    - Nazi Operations, Colombia and Panama (Box 39)
    - Passports (Box 39)
    - Works by others (Box 39)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 40)
    - 1935-1938 (Box 40)
    - 1939 (Box 41)
    - 1939-1942; (numbered) 1, 2 - 1942 (Box 42)
    - 2a-4 - 1942 (Box 43)
    - 5, 6 - 1942 (Box 44)
    - 7, 8 - 1943 (Box 45)
    - 9, 10 - 1943 (Box 46)
    - 11-13 - 1944 (Box 47)
    - 14, 15 - 1944 (Box 48)
    - 16, 17 and unnumbered (Box 49)
    - 19, 20 (Box 50)
  - Scrapbooks end clippings, miscellaneous (Box 51)
  - Scrapbook and photographs, miscellaneous (Box 52)
  - Clippings, 1937-1947 (Box 53)
  - Clippings, ca. 1938 and miscellaneous printed (Box 54)
  - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 55)
  - Photographs, tapes, awards, movie film and related items (Box 56)
  - Pamphlets: Peronist, ultraconservative, others, tapes and movie film continued (Box 57)
  - Clippings and Periodicals (Box 58)
  - Printed miscellany (Box 59)
  - Catalogued photographs (Box 59)
  - OVERSIZE; Photographs and Documents (Box Map Cases 14-P-2 and 14-P-3)
  - OVERSIZE: Phonograph records of speeches and miscellaneous events - 1 Folder (Box Flat Box 30)
  - OVERSIZE: Report: Argentinian and German Activities (Box CMI Box 71)
  - Scrapbook - 1 volume (Box CMI Box 72)
  - Inscribed books (Box 60-66)
  - Annotated books (Box 67-70)